Finding Aid for Elizabeth H. Giese papers, 1971-1992 and 1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Elizabeth H. Giese papers 1971-1992, 1997, 1979-1984
Giese, Elizabeth H., 1943-
3.5 linear feet
9771 Aa 2
Giese served as director of the Michigan Project on Equal Education Rights (PEER), a division of the National Organization for Women's Legal Defense and Education Fund, from 1978 to 1984. The collection also contains files on Michigan women in high school athletics, vocational education courses, math classes, and science classes. Other files relate to legal cases on sex discrimination, the Michigan Women's Hall of Fame, and all-male academies in Detroit.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 8544 ) was received from Elizabeth Homer in December 1996.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Born in 1943, Elizabeth Giese received her bachelor's degree in education from the University of Michigan in 1964 and an M.A. degree in Occupational Administration from Ferris State College in 1986. After teaching at the elementary and preschool levels, Giese accepted a position as the first director of the Michigan Project on Equal Education Rights (PEER) in 1978.
PEER was organized in 1974 by the National Organization for Women's Legal Defense and Education Fund to lobby for the enforcement of Title IX and other regulations relating to sex equity in the schools. In 1978, PEER applied for and received a grant from the Mott Foundation to set up a pilot project in Michigan to create a model which other states might follow. The result of this effort was a manual for state PEER organizations called Organizing for Change based largely on the experience of Michigan PEER.
Headquartered in Milford, Michigan, PEER's primary mission was to organize and support local branches of PEER, which would then advocate gender equity in education at the town, district or county level. These local groups used a variety of tactics directed at teachers, school boards, and administrators. For the most part, cooperation and communication were their preferred methods. In addition, the groups used surveys, interviews and other data collection instruments to measure local compliance with Title IX and increase awareness of gender inequality in education.
In support of local groups, Michigan PEER offered workshops and provided a wide variety of information resources. In addition to distributing basic manuals on organizing and collecting data, Michigan PEER operated a clearinghouse of materials related to sex equity in education. Periodically, PEER coordinated large data collection projects which involved some or all of the local groups. Most prominently, in 1980, every local PEER group in Michigan compiled a report on teacher attitudes and Title IX compliance within their school district. The state office synthesized the local results into a widely publicized document entitled You See the Cat Walking. Several subjects were of special interest to PEER: the teaching of math and science, vocational education and training, and school athletics. Finally, the Michigan PEER office was active in using media outlets to publicize its activities and research.
At the state level, Michigan PEER played a crucial role in a network of individuals and organizations interested in issues relating to women and education. The Coalition for Non-Sexist Education, and the Office of Sex Equity in Education were the most prominent among several such groups in Michigan. PEER's advisory board, made up of prominent citizens and activists, also served an important function in this network. In addition to supporting community groups, these groups cooperated at the state level to promote change through the legislature, the courts, the Department of Education, and the Michigan High School Athletic Association.
After leaving PEER in 1984, Giese served as a consultant to the Michigan Department of Labor's Bureau of Vocational Education and the Michigan Department of Education (where she had consulted since 1980). In 1987, she accepted an appointment as the director of the Michigan Women's Hall of Fame, and beginning in 1989, Giese chaired the National Organization for Women's Education Task Force. In 1990, the Task Force initiated a successful lawsuit in conjunction with the Michigan ACLU against the Detroit School Board, which had proposed all-male academies in Detroit.
The papers of Elizabeth Giese have been divided into six series: Biographical File, PEER Files, Subject Files, Legal Cases on Sex Discrimination, Women's Rights Organizations, Math and Science, and Vocational Education. The bulk of the material in this collection relates to the activities of Michigan PEER. However, it is sometimes difficult to distinguish materials related to Giese's role as a citizen, activist and consultant from materials collected in her official capacity as an employee of Michigan PEER. The organization of the collection occasionally reflects this fact. Some of the series, and some individual files, are organized around particular subjects, rather than Giese's professional or personal activities.
Subjects:
Citizens advisory committees in education.; Community organization--Michigan.; NOW Legal Defense & Education Fund.; Sex discrimination against women--Michigan.; Sex discrimination in education--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Sex discrimination in education--Michigan.; Sex discrimination in sports--Michigan.; Sports for women--Michigan.; Vocational education--Michigan.; Women--Vocational education--Michigan.; Women in mathematics--Michigan.; Women in community organization--Michigan.; Women's rights--Michigan.; Women political activists--Michigan.; Michigan Project on Equal Education Rights.
Contributors:
Michigan. Office for Sex Equity in Education.; Michigan High School Athletic Association.; Michigan Women's Assembly.; Coalition for Non-Sexist Education.
- Biographical File
  - Resume (Box 1)
- Michigan PEER Files
  The Michigan PEER Files, 1979-1983, consists partly of communications between the central office, the local PEER committees, and the PEER Advisory board. Other files include copies of the organizing manuals (some written by the state PEER office) used to educate local activists. The "Site Progress Reports" contain several short reports from the local PEER committee documenting their various activities. The comprehensive survey undertaken by each local committee in 1981 and 1982 has been documented with a sampling of reports. The synthesis of these local efforts, often referred to as You See the Cat Walking, can be found in the University of Michigan's Hatcher Graduate Library (in the ERIC microfilm sets). Two files concern the workshops designed to train and educate local activists. Also included are publicity materials, such as press releases, brochures and informational handouts. Especially useful in documenting the group's concerns and activities, the series contains a complete run of the newsletter, Michigan PEER Perspective, for the years 1979 to 1983. A few articles on the subject of Michigan PEER, written for conferences or publication, are also included in this series.
  - Advisory Board 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Data Collection Instruments Undated (Box 1)
  - Endorsement Letters 1978-1982 (Box 1)
  - Media Relations and Publicity
    - General Undated (Box 1)
    - Math, Science and Vocational Education 1983-1984, undated (Box 1)
    - Press Releases 1979-1982, undated (Box 1)
  - Organizing Manuals
    - Cracking the Glass Slipper, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Getting Your Money's Worth, Undated (Box 1)
    - Interview Manual, Undated (Box 1)
    - Manual for Local Coalitions, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Organizing for Change, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Statistical Data, Undated (Box 1)
  - PEER Perspective, 1979-1983 (Box 1)
  - Press Clippings
    A sub-series within the Michigan PEER Files, "Press Clippings," has been organized alphabetically. Most files contain articles from local or regional newspapers related to the topics of sex equity and PEER activity within a specific town or county. Hence, the bulk of the articles date from 1979 to 1984. A few files were organized around subject rather than locality. For instance, one file includes articles publicizing PEER's 1981 report on gender bias in Michigan schools.
    - Alma area 1979 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor area 1979-1983 (Box 1)
    - Athletics 1984-1989 (Box 1)
    - Bloomfield Hills area 1979-1982 (Box 1)
    - Brighton area 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - Detroit area 1977-1983, undated (Box 1)
    - Grand Rapids area 1979-1982 (Box 1)
    - Flint area 1980 (Box 1)
    - Jackson area 1979-1983 (Box 1)
    - Kalamazoo area 1979-1983 (Box 1)
    - Lansing area 1979-1983 (Box 1)
    - Livingston County area 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - PEER study of sex bias in Michigan schools 1981 (Box 1)
    - Marquette area 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Milford area 1979-1983 (Box 1)
    - Midland area 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1979-1980, undated (Box 1)
    - Mt. Clemens area 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Muskegon area 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Novi area 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - Oakland area 1980-1983 (Box 1)
    - Sex Role Stereotyping 1979-1990 (Box 1)
    - Southwest Michigan 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Reports and Proposals
    A second sub-series, "Reports and Proposals," consists primarily of grant proposals, and reports to funding agencies such as the Mott Foundation and the Ford Foundation. Since Michigan PEER was primarily funded through grants, these reports and proposals offer an excellent summary of the group's goals and accomplishments. The series has been arranged chronologically.
    - Mott Foundation Grant 1979-1980
      - Proposal 1979 (Box 1)
      - Progress Report 1979 (Box 1)
      - Progress Report 1980 (Box 1)
      - Progress Report 1980 (Box 1)
    - PEER/Michigan Association of School Administrators Grant Proposal 1980 (Box 1)
    - Ford Foundation Grant
      - Draft Proposal 1981 (Box 1)
      - Progress Reports 1981-1983 (Box 1)
      - Quarterly Reports 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - Seed Grants Proposals
      - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
      - 1983-1984, undated (Box 1)
    - Proposal for 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - School Surveys and Reports
    - Ann Arbor (Box 2)
    - Detroit (Box 2)
    - Grand Haven (Box 2)
    - Lansing (Box 2)
  - Site Coordinator Communications (Box 2)
  - Site Progress Reports
    - 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Workshops
    - Leadership on Equity Project (Box 2)
    - Training Workshop (Box 2)
  - Writings
    - Burkholder, Donald (Box 2)
    - Davies, Alice (Box 2)
    - Giese, Elizabeth (Box 2)
- Subject Files
  The Subject Files, 1971-1993, contain material on several topics relating to sex equity in education. Most of these files date from Giese's years as director of PEER and concern equity in high school athletics, equal opportunity for female school administrators, and legislation related to equity in education. Other topics covered in this series are the creation and planning of the Michigan Women's Hall of Fame (including promotional and educational materials related to women's history in Michigan), the Huron Valley school system (where Giese was a parent and concerned citizen), pre-1978 efforts to enforce sex equity in Michigan, and the fight in the early 1990s against all-male academies in Detroit. Most of these files contain a variety of material, including letters, memos, notes, reports and news clippings.
  - All Male Academies 1990-1992 (Box 2)
  - Girls in Sports
    - County Athletic Reports (Box 2)
    - Cutback in Girls' Sports (Box 2)
    - Girls and Contact Sports (Box 2)
    - Growth in Girls' Sports (Box 2)
    - Interscholastic Task Force Report 1979 (Box 2)
    - Short History of Girls' Interscholastic Sports in Michigan, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Soccer (Box 2)
  - Historical Files
    - Pre-Title IX reports on sex equity 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - Federbush, Marcia 1973-1977 (Box 2)
  - Huron Valley (Box 2)
  - Legislation
    - Michigan 1981-1993, undated (Box 2)
    - National 1980-1982, undated (Box 2)
  - Michigan History 1986 undated (Box 2)
  - Michigan Women's Hall of Fame
    - Correspondence 1979-1983, undated (Box 2)
    - How the Suffragists Changed Michigan (an educational packet) (Box 2)
    - Handouts and Brochures (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Pregnant Students 1977-1982 (Box 2)
  - Sexual Harassment in Schools 1992-1994 (Box 2)
  - State Superintendent for Public Instruction 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan 1979-1981, undated (Box 2)
  - Women and the Law (Box 2)
  - Women in Administration 1978-1984, undated (Box 2)
  - Western Michigan University 1979 (Box 2)
- Legal Cases on Sex Discrimination
  The Legal Cases on Sex Discrimination Series concerns legal suits on sex discrimination in sports. It includes materials related to suits against the Ann Arbor School Board (on behalf of a female student who was denied permission to join the high school golf team), a suit against Michigan State University by the women's basketball team, and several suits against the Michigan High School Athletics Association. This series also has newspaper reactions to the ruling of Judge Charles Joiner. PEER's role in these lawsuits is unclear.
  - Ann Arbor
    - Golf 1979 (Box 2)
    - Joiner Ruling
      - Reactions 1981 (Box 2)
      - Ruling (Box 2)
      - US Department of Education 1983 (Box 2)
  - Grove City 1984 (Box 3)
  - Michigan State University 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - Michigan High School Athletic Association
    - Sex Charges, 1977-82, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - MHSAA vs. Office of Civil Rights 1982 (Box 3)
    - Complaint 1979-1983, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Paper Clippings 1980-1984 (Box 3)
    - Suit Dismissed 1983 (Box 3)
    - Reactions (Box 3)
  - Redford Union School 1981 (Box 3)
  - Waterford 1983 (Box 3)
  - Women Coaches 1979-1980 (Box 3)
- Women's Rights Organizations
  The Women's Rights Organizations Series includes memos, letters and reports from the Coalition for Non-Sexist Education, an organization created in 1976 as a result of the frustration felt by many women over the lack of enforcement of Title IX and other anti-discrimination statutes. Here there are also documents relating to the Women Coaches Advocacy Group, Women's Assembly III, and a report of the Women's Task Force on Title IX. Giese contributed her time to some of these organizations, helping to write reports, and corresponding with other members.
  - Coalition Non-Sexist Education, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Office of Sex Equity in Education
    - Compliance with Title IX Report 1979 (Box 3)
    - Jo Jacobs, director (Box 3)
    - Pregnant Students Report 1991 (Box 3)
    - Publications, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Socialization Report 1989-1991 (Box 3)
  - Sex and Race Equity Assessment Report 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Women's Rights Organization (Box 3)
  - WEAL Publications (Box 3)
  - Women's Assembly III (Box 3)
  - Women Coaches Advocacy Group (Box 3)
  - Women's Task Force, Report 1980 (Box 3)
- Math and Science
  The Math and Science Series, 1974-1983, contains documents pertaining in part to the limited number of students in Michigan receiving Math and Science education. Elizabeth Giese conducted a study which showed a drop in the number of students taking math, especially girls. With this study PEER was hoping to raise the awareness of educators of the need for better math preparation from elementary through high school. Some of these files relate to PEER activities, while some derive from other sources.
  - Computers and Girls 1983 (Box 3)
  - Math and Jobs 1981 (Box 3)
  - Math Paper Clippings 1979-1989 (Box 3)
  - Math Publications 1980, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Math Study, Elizabeth Giese 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Science Studies 1983 (Box 4)
  - Women's Committee--Sexism in Math 1974 (Box 4)
  - Women in Math and Science (Box 4)
  - Women, Math and Science Manual (Box 4)
- Vocational Education
  The Vocational Education Series, 1979-1993, consists of materials documenting the importance of vocational education in preparing students for employment and continued education. In 1989, the Michigan State Board of Education authorized an in-depth study on Vocational-Technical Education (VTE) outlining job demands and directions for change in the 21st Century. This series also has correspondence and reactions relating to a paper written by Liz Giese titled, "Are we educating our girls to be poor?"
  - Correspondence 1987-1993 Elizabeth Giese (Box 4)
  - Elizabeth Giese's Writings (Box 4)
  - Macomb County, Equal Employment Opportunity (Box 4)
  - Programs and Reports (Box 4)
  - Publications, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - State Plan Executive Summary (Box 4)
  - Strategic Plans for Vocational Education 1990 (Box 4)
  - Technical education 1979-1990 (Box 4)
  - Vocational Education Status in Michigan and the Press (Box 4)
- Other materials
  - Report 1997 entitled "Title IX in Michigan, 1972-1997" by Elizabeth Giese Homer (Box 4)